For a long time,
لفترة طويلة،
there was me, and my body.
كان هناك (أنا =ذهني ) وكان هناك جسدي
Me was composed of stories,
(أنا) كانت تتألف من القصص ،
of cravings, of strivings,
من الرغبات الشديدة، والمطامح،
of desires of the future.
رغبات في المستقبل
Me was trying
(أنا) كانت تحاول
not to be an outcome of my violent past,
أن لا تكون نتاج الماضي العنيف ،
but the separation that had already occurred
لكن الانفصال الذي حدث بالفعل
between me and my body
بيني وبين جسدي
was a pretty significant outcome.
كانت نتيجته كبيرة جدا.
Me was always trying to become something, somebody.
(أنا) كانت تحاول دائما أن تصبح شيئا ما ، شخص ما.
Me only existed in the trying.
(أنا) كانت موجودة فقط في المحاولة.
My body was often in the way.
كان جسدي في كثير من الأحيان في الطريق.
Me was a floating head.
(أنا) كانت الذهن العائم .
For years, I actually only wore hats.
لسنوات ، كنت أرتدي قبعات .
It was a way of keeping my head attached.
كانت تلك الوسيلة لابقي ذهني على إتصال .
It was a way of locating myself.
كان وسيلة لتحديد مكان نفسي.
I worried that [if] I took my hat off
كنت أخشى أنه إذا خلعت قبعتي
I wouldn't be here anymore.
لن أكون هنا بعد الآن.
I actually had a therapist who once said to me,
قال لي الطبيب ذات مرة ،
"Eve, you've been coming here for two years,
ايف ، انت تأتين الى هنا منذ سنتين
and, to be honest, it never occurred to me that you had a body."
و لأكون صادقاً ، لم يخطر لي أنه كان لديك جسد ".
All this time I lived in the city
كل هذا الوقت كنت أعيش في المدينة ،
because, to be honest,
لأنه ، لأكون صادقة ،
I was afraid of trees.
كنت خائفة من الأشجار.
I never had babies
لم يكن لي أطفال
because heads cannot give birth.
لأن الاذهان لا تلد.
Babies actually don't come out of your mouth.
الأطفال في الواقع لا يخرجون من فمك.
As I had no reference point for my body,
كما لم يكن لدي نقطة مرجعية لجسدي ،
I began to ask other women about their bodies --
بدأت أسئل نساء أخريات عن اجسامهن --
in particular, their vaginas,
على وجه الخصوص ، مهابلهن،
because I thought vaginas were kind of important.
لأني اعتقدت أن المهابل لها نوع من الأهمية
This led to me writing "The Vagina Monologues,"
دفعني ذلك لكتابة "مناجاة المهبل"
which led to me obsessively and incessantly
وذلك قادني إلى هوس غير متوقف
talking about vaginas everywhere I could.
الحديث عن المهابل في كل مكان أستطيع.
I did this in front of many strangers.
فعلت ذلك أمام الكثير من الغرباء .
One night on stage,
أحدى الليالي على خشبة المسرح
I actually entered my vagina.
في الحقيقة دخلت في مهبلي
It was an ecstatic experience.
كانت تجربة النشوة.
It scared me, it energized me,
لقد أخافتني ، و أمدتني بالنّشاط
and then I became a driven person,
وبعد ذلك اصبحت أنسانة مقادة ،
a driven vagina.
مقادة بالمهبل
I began to see my body like a thing,
بدأت أرى جسدي وكأنه شيء ،
a thing that could move fast,
شيئ يمكن أن يتحرك بسرعة ،
like a thing that could accomplish other things,
كشيئ يستطيع أن ينجز أشياء أخرى
many things, all at once.
الكثير من الأشياء ، جميعها في نفس الوقت
I began to see my body like an iPad or a car.
بدأت أرى جسدي مثل (أي باد) أو سيارة.
I would drive it and demand things from it.
يمكنني أن أقوده و أطلب منه أشياء
It had no limits. It was invincible.
ولم يكن له حدود . كان لا يقهر.
It was to be conquered and mastered like the Earth herself.
كان لابد أن يغزو ويسود كالأرض نفسها
I didn't heed it;
لم أكن انصاع إليه ؛
no, I organized it and I directed it.
بل ، نظمته ووجهته
I didn't have patience for my body;
لم يكن لدي صبر على جسدي؛
I snapped it into shape.
ضغطه في شكل
I was greedy.
كنت جشعة.
I took more than my body had to offer.
لقد أخذت من جسدي اكثر مما عرضه علي
If I was tired, I drank more espressos.
إذا كنت متعبة، أشرب المزيد من الإسبريسو.
If I was afraid, I went to more dangerous places.
إذا كنت خائفة، كنت أذهب إلى أماكن أكثر خطورة.
Oh sure, sure, I had moments of appreciation of my body,
أوه بالتأكيد، بالتأكيد، كان لي لحظات من التقدير من جسدي،
the way an abusive parent
على طريقة التعسفية أحد الوالدين
can sometimes have a moment of kindness.
أحيانا يمكن أن يكون لديه لحظة عطف
My father was really kind to me
والدي كان لطيفا معي حقاً
on my 16th birthday, for example.
في عيد ميلادي 16، على سبيل المثال .
I heard people murmur from time to time
سمعت بعض همهمة الناس
that I should love my body,
أن علي أن احب جسدي
so I learned how to do this.
لذا فإنني تعلمت كيفية القيام بذلك.
I was a vegetarian, I was sober, I didn't smoke.
كنت نباتية ، كنت واعية ، لم اكن أدخن
But all that was just a more sophisticated way
ولكن كل هذا كان فقط مزيدا من الطرق الراقية
to manipulate my body --
لمعالجة جسدي --
a further disassociation,
إنفصال أبعد
like planting a vegetable field on a freeway.
مثل زراعة الخضار في الميادين المحاذية للطريق السريع
As a result of me talking so much about my vagina,
ونتيجة لتكلمي بكثرة عن مهبلي
many women started to tell me about theirs --
بدأت العديد من النساء ليقول لي عن رغبتهم --
their stories about their bodies.
في رواية القصص عن أجسادهن
Actually, these stories compelled me around the world,
في الحقيقة ، تلك القصص أجبرتني على الطواف حول العالم
and I've been to over 60 countries.
ولقد زرت أكثر من 60 دولة
I heard thousands of stories,
سمعت الآلاف من القصص.
and I have to tell you, there was always this moment
وأود أن أقول لكم ، هذه اللحظة موجودة دوماً
where the women shared with me
عندما تشاركني المرأة
that particular moment when she separated from her body --
تلك اللحظة بالذات عندما تنفصل عن جسدها
when she left home.
عندما غادرت المنزل
I heard about women being molested in their beds,
سمعت عن نساء يتعرضون للأذى في أسرّتهم،
flogged in their burqas,
يجلدن داخل نقابهن
left for dead in parking lots,
تركن ليموتوا في مواقف السيارات،
acid burned in their kitchens.
أحرق الحامض في مطابخهن
Some women became quiet and disappeared.
بعض النساء تم قتلهن أو أختفين .
Other women became mad, driven machines like me.
وأصبحت النساء الأخريات مصابات بالجنون ، وآلات مقادة مثلي.
In the middle of my traveling,
في منتصف سفري ،
I turned 40 and I began to hate my body,
وبلغت سن الـ 40، وبدأت أكره جسدي ،
which was actually progress,
الذي كان في الواقع متقدم ،
because at least my body existed enough to hate it.
لأنه على الأقل جسدي كان موجود لكي أهينه
Well my stomach -- it was my stomach I hated.
كذلك معدتي -- كانت المعدة التي كرهت.
It was proof that I had not measured up,
كان هناك دليل على أنها لم ترتق الى المستوى
that I was old and not fabulous and not perfect
كنت عجوزاً ولست رائعة أو كاملة
or able to fit into the predetermined corporate image in shape.
أو قادرة على التوائم مع شكل صورة الشركات المحددة مسبقاً
My stomach was proof that I had failed,
كانت معدتي دليلا على أني قد فشلت ،
that it had failed me, that it was broken.
التي كانت قد فشلت ، والتي تم كسرها.
My life became about getting rid of it and obsessing about getting rid of it.
أصبحت حياتي حول التخلص منها ، والتفكير المهووس حول التخلص منها.
In fact, it became so extreme
في الحقيقة ، أصبحت أكثر تطرفاً
I wrote a play about it.
كتبت مسرحية عنها
But the more I talked about it,
ولكن كل ما تحدثت عنه أكثر
the more objectified and fragmented my body became.
كلما أصبح جسدي "شيئا" كأجزاء
It became entertainment; it became a new kind of commodity,
فقد أصبح تسلية ونوع جديد من السلع
something I was selling.
شيء كنت أبيعه .
Then I went somewhere else.
ثم ذهبت إلى مكان آخر.
I went outside
ذهبت خارجاً
what I thought I knew.
ما كنت أعتقد أنني أعرفه.
I went to the Democratic Republic of Congo.
ذهبت إلى جمهورية الكونغو الديمقراطية.
And I heard stories
وسمعت القصص
that shattered all the other stories.
التي حطمت جميع القصص الأخرى.
I heard stories
سمعت قصصاً
that got inside my body.
حصلت داخل جسدي.
I heard about a little girl
سمعت عن فتاة صغيرة
who couldn't stop peeing on herself
التي لم تستطع وقف التبول على نفسها
because so many grown soldiers
بسبب الكثير من الجنود المحدثين
had shoved themselves inside her.
حشروا أنفسهم داخلها
I heard an 80-year-old woman
سمعت عن إمرأة تبلغ 80 عاماً
whose legs were broken and pulled out of her sockets
قدميها كسرتا وسحبت من مقابضها
and twisted up on her head
ولفت على رأسها
as the soldiers raped her like that.
كما اغتصبها جنود كذلك
There are thousands of these stories,
هناك الآلاف من هذه القصص.
and many of the women had holes in their bodies --
و هناك العديد من النساء الذين لديهن ثقوب بأجسادهن
holes, fistula --
الثقوب، والناسور --
that were the violation of war --
وكان ذلك انتهاكات للحرب --
holes in the fabric of their souls.
ثقوب في نسيج أرواحهن
These stories saturated my cells and nerves,
هذه القصص أشبعت خلاياي وأعصابي
and to be honest,
ولكي أكون صادقة
I stopped sleeping for three years.
توقفت عن النوم لمدة ثلاث سنوات.
All the stories began to bleed together.
وبدأت جميع القصص تنزفن معا.
The raping of the Earth,
واغتصاب الأرض ،
the pillaging of minerals,
نهب المعادن ،
the destruction of vaginas --
تدمير المهابل --
none of these were separate anymore
لا أحد من
from each other or me.
من بعضها البعض أو منّي.
Militias were raping six-month-old babies
وقامت الميليشيات باغتصاب أطفال ذوي ستة شهور
so that countries far away
بحيث تستطيع البلدان البعيدة عنهم
could get access to gold and coltan
الحصول على الذهب والكولتان
for their iPhones and computers.
لأجهزتهم الآيفون و حواسيبهم .
My body had not only become a driven machine,
وجسدي لم يعد ماكنة مدفوعة فقط
but it was responsible now
ولكنه أصبح مسؤولا الآن
for destroying other women's bodies
عن تدمير اجسدة النساء الأخريات
in its mad quest to make more machines
في سعيها المجنون لكسب المزيد من الآلات
to support the speed and efficiency of my machine.
لدعم سرعة وكفاءة جهازي.
Then I got cancer --
ثم أصبت بالسرطان
or I found out I had cancer.
أو اكتشفت أنني مصابة بالسرطان.
It arrived like a speeding bird
ووصل الأمر وكأنه طائر مسرع
smashing into a windowpane.
ارتطم بأحد أجزاء النافذة.
Suddenly, I had a body,
فجأة، وجدت جسدي ،
a body that was pricked
جسد موخوذ
and poked and punctured,
مطعون ومثقوب ،
a body that was cut wide open,
جسد مقطوع عرضاً وشق
a body that had organs removed
جسد كانت اعضائه مزالة
and transported and rearranged and reconstructed,
ونقلها وإعادة ترتيبها واعادة بنائها،
a body that was scanned
جسد قد تم مسحه
and had tubes shoved down it,
والأنابيب التي حشرت في أعماقه
a body that was burning from chemicals.
جسد كان يحترق من الكيماويات
Cancer exploded
انفجر السرطان
the wall of my disconnection.
جدار عزلتي
I suddenly understood that the crisis in my body
فهمت فجأة أن الأزمة في جسدي
was the crisis in the world,
كانت الأزمة في العالم ،
and it wasn't happening later,
ولم تكن تحدث لاحقاً
it was happening now.
كانت ذلك يحدث الآن.
Suddenly, my cancer was a cancer that was everywhere,
فجأة ، سرطاني كان السرطان الذي كان في كل مكان،
the cancer of cruelty, the cancer of greed,
السرطان من القسوة، وسرطان الجشع ،
the cancer that gets inside people
السرطان الذي يحصل داخل الشعب
who live down the streets from chemical plants -- and they're usually poor --
الذين يعيشون في الشوارع القريبة من المصانع الكيماوية -- وهم في العادة ما تكون فقيرة --
the cancer inside the coal miner's lungs,
سرطان الرئتين داخل منجم للفحم،
the cancer of stress for not achieving enough,
السرطان من الإجهاد لعدم تحقيق ما يكفي،
the cancer of buried trauma,
السرطان من الصدمة المدفونة ،
the cancer in caged chickens and polluted fish,
السرطان في قفص الدجاج والسمك الملوث،
the cancer in women's uteruses from being raped,
السرطان في الأرحام النساء جراء التعرض للاغتصاب،
the cancer that is everywhere from our carelessness.
السرطان الذي هو في كل مكان نتيجة لا مبالاتنا
In his new and visionary book,
في كتابه الجديد والبصيرة ،
"New Self, New World,"
"الذات الجديدة ، العالم الجديد"
the writer Philip Shepherd says,
الكاتب فيليب شيبرد يقول :
"If you are divided from your body,
"اذا كنت منفصل عن جسدك ،
you are also divided from the body of the world,
فأنت منفصل أيضا من جسد العالم ،
which then appears to be other than you
والذي يظهر حينئذ مختلفا عنك
or separate from you,
او منفصلا عنك
rather than the living continuum
بدلا من استمرارية المعيشة
to which you belong."
التي تنتمي إليها ".
Before cancer,
قبل السرطان ،
the world was something other.
كان العالم شيء آخر.
It was as if I was living in a stagnant pool
كان كما لو كنت أعيش في بركة راكدة
and cancer dynamited the boulder
والسرطان فجر الصخرة
that was separating me from the larger sea.
التي تفصل بيني وبين البحر الأكبر
Now I am swimming in it.
انا الأن أسبح فيه
Now I lay down in the grass
الأن أنا أستلقي على العشب
and I rub my body in it,
وأفرك جسدي فيه،
and I love the mud on my legs and feet.
وأحب الطين على ساقي و قدمي
Now I make a daily pilgrimage
أنا الآن أقوم بالحج يومياً
to visit a particular weeping willow by the Seine,
لزيارة الصفصاف الباكية ولا سيما عن طريق نهر السين،
and I hunger for the green fields
وأنا جائعة للحقول الخضراء
in the bush outside Bukavu.
في الادغال خارج بوكافو.
And when it rains hard rain,
وعندما تمطر المطر الغزير،
I scream and I run in circles.
أنا أصرخ وأركض في حلقة مفرغة.
I know that everything is connected,
وأنا أعرف أن كل شيء متصل،
and the scar that runs the length of my torso
والندب التي إمتد على طول الجذع من بلدي
is the markings of the earthquake.
هي من علامات وقوع الزلزال.
And I am there with the three million in the streets of Port-au-Prince.
وانا هناك مع ثلاثة ملايين في شوارع بورت أو برنس.
And the fire that burned in me
والنار التي تحرق في داخلي
on day three through six of chemo
في اليوم الثالث للعلاج الكيميائي للسرطان
is the fire that is burning
هي النار التي تحترق
in the forests of the world.
في غابات العالم.
I know that the abscess
وأنا أعرف أن الخراج (الصديد )
that grew around my wound after the operation,
الذي نما حول الجرح بعد العملية
the 16 ounces of puss,
ال16 أوقية من السنور،
is the contaminated Gulf of Mexico,
التي تلوث خليج المكسيك
and there were oil-drenched pelicans inside me
وكان هناك نفط منقوع البجعات بداخلي
and dead floating fish.
والأسماك العائمة الميتة .
And the catheters they shoved into me without proper medication
و القساطرة الذين شقوا فيّ بدون علاج مناسب
made me scream out
جعلني أصرخ
the way the Earth cries out from the drilling.
بالطريقة التي تصرخ بها الأرض من الحفر.
In my second chemo,
في جلسة العلاج الكيميائي الثانية
my mother got very sick
أمي كانت مريضة جداً
and I went to see her.
وكنت أريد رؤيتها
And in the name of connectedness,
وبأسم الترابط والتواصل،
the only thing she wanted before she died
الشيء الوحيد الذي أرادت قبل وفاتها
was to be brought home
هو أن تعود الى المنزل .
by her beloved Gulf of Mexico.
بالقرب من حبيبها خليج المكسيك.
So we brought her home,
لذلك أحضرناها للمنزل ،
and I prayed that the oil wouldn't wash up on her beach
وصليت أن لا يغسل النفط شاطئها
before she died.
قبل وفاتها.
And gratefully, it didn't.
وبامتنان، لم يصل النفط الى هناك.
And she died quietly in her favorite place.
وتوفيت بهدوء في مكانها المفضل.
And a few weeks later, I was in New Orleans,
وبعد بضعة أسابيع، كنت في نيو أورليانز ،
and this beautiful, spiritual friend
وقد أخبرتني صديقتي الروحانية
told me she wanted to do a healing for me.
بأنها كانت تريد أن تشفيني
And I was honored.
وكان لي ذلك الشرف.
And I went to her house, and it was morning,
وذهبت الى منزلها، في الصباح،
and the morning New Orleans sun was filtering through the curtains.
وكان صباح نيو اورليانز يتصفى من خلال الستائر.
And my friend was preparing this big bowl,
وصديقتي تحضّر السلطانية الكبيرة ،
and I said, "What is it?"
فسألت : "ما هو؟"
And she said, "It's for you.
فقالت "انها لك.
The flowers make it beautiful,
الزهور تجعلها جميلة ،
and the honey makes it sweet."
و العسل يجعلها حلوة
And I said, "But what's the water part?"
وقلت : "لكن ماذا يعني وجود المياه؟"
And in the name of connectedness,
وبشيء من الترابط،
she said, "Oh, it's the Gulf of Mexico."
قالت : "أوه، انه خليج المكسيك."
And I said, "Of course it is."
فقلت : "بالطبع هو كذلك."
And the other women arrived and they sat in a circle,
ووصلت النسوة الأخريات وجلسن في دائرة ،
and Michaela bathed my head with the sacred water.
وحممت "ميشلا" رأسي في الماء المقدس.
And she sang -- I mean her whole body sang.
وغنت -- أعني أن جسدها كله غنى.
And the other women sang
وغنت بقية النساء
and they prayed for me and my mother.
وصلوا لي ولوالدتي.
And as the warm Gulf washed over my naked head,
وكما في الخليج الدافئ تغسل رأسي العاري
I realized that it held
أدركت أنه يحوي
the best and the worst of us.
أفضل وأسوأ ما فينا.
It was the greed and recklessness
كان الجشع والتهور
that led to the drilling explosion.
الذي قاد إلى تفجر حفر التنقيب
It was all the lies that got told
كان كل الأكاذيب التي صُرح بها
before and after.
قبل وبعد التسرب النفطي
It was the honey in the water that made it sweet,
كان هناك عسل في المياه مما جعله حلو
it was the oil that made it sick.
كان هناك زيت مما جعله مريض
It was my head that was bald --
كان رأسي الذي كان أصلع
and comfortable now without a hat.
و مرتاح الآن من دون قبعة
It was my whole self
كانت نفسي كلها
melting into Michaela's lap.
تذوب في حضن ميشلا
It was the tears that were indistinguishable from the Gulf
كانت الدموع التي لا يمكن تمييزها عن الخليج
that were falling down my cheek.
التي كانت تسقط من وجنتي
It was finally being in my body.
وتنتهي في جسدي
It was the sorrow
كان الحزن
that's taken so long.
الذي أستمر طويلاً
It was finding my place
كان يعثر على مكاني
and the huge responsibility
والمسؤولية ضخمة
that comes with connection.
التي تأتي مع الاتصال.
It was the continuing devastating war in the Congo
كان استمرار الحرب المدمرة في الكونغو
and the indifference of the world.
واللامبالاة في العالم.
It was the Congolese women
وكانت المرأة الكونغولية
who are now rising up.
التي تنهض الآن
It was my mother leaving,
كانت والدتي تحتضر و تغادر،
just at the moment
خلال اللحظات
that I was being born.
التي ولدت فيها
It was the realization
لقد كان إدراك
that I had come very close to dying --
اني كنت قد اقتربت جدا من الموت --
in the same way that the Earth, our mother,
بنفس الطريقة التي تصمد بها
is barely holding on,
بالكاد الأرض ، أمنّا ،
in the same way that 75 percent of the planet
بنفس الطريقة نفسها التي يزال بها 75 بالمائة
are hardly scraping by,
من كوكب الأرض
in the same way
في نفس الطريق
that there is a recipe for survival.
أن هناك وصفة للبقاء على قيد الحياة.
What I learned
ما تعلمته
is it has to do with attention and resources
أن هناك علاقة بين المبالاة والموارد
that everybody deserves.
وأن الجميع يستحقها.
It was advocating friends
كانت الدعوة إلى الأصدقاء
and a doting sister.
وشقيقة شغوفه.
It was wise doctors and advanced medicine
كان حكمة الأطباء والطب المتقدم
and surgeons who knew what to do with their hands.
والجراحين الذين يعرفون ما يجب القيام به بأيديهم.
It was underpaid and really loving nurses.
لقد كان أجراً متدنياً لممرضات محبوبات حقاً
It was magic healers and aromatic oils.
لقد كان علاجاً ناجعاً وزيتا عاطراً
It was people who came with spells and rituals.
لقد كان من الناس الذين جاءوا بالسحر والطقوس.
It was having a vision of the future
كان كامتلاك رؤية للمستقبل
and something to fight for,
وشيء تكافح من أجله
because I know this struggle isn't my own.
لأنني أعرف هذا الصراع ليس صراعي.
It was a million prayers.
كان مثل مليون مُصلّي.
It was a thousand hallelujahs
وألف تسبيح
and a million oms.
ومليون دعاء
It was a lot of anger,
كان هناك الكثير من الغضب
insane humor,
فكاهة مجنونة ،
a lot of attention, outrage.
الكثير من الاهتمام ، والغضب.
It was energy, love and joy.
كان من الطاقة والحب والمتعة.
It was all these things.
كانت كل هذه الأشياء.
in the water, in the world, in my body.
في الماء ، في العالم ، في جسدي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)